<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Neuues from Millaine the copie of a letter written from Millaine to Venice, by Signior Padre, concerning a strange prince, called Prince Mammon, who is lately come into that state, and hath taken vp one of the principall houses (belonging to a chiefe noble-man of that countrey) for himselfe and followers ... / translated out of the true Italian copie ; also, the abridgement of the articles of pacification of Italie, made betwixt his Imperiall Maiesty and the most Christian King at Ratisbone, the 13th of October, 1630, both in Latine and English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17916.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4387</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24251890</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24251890</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1821:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Neuues from Millaine the copie of a letter written from Millaine to Venice, by Signior Padre, concerning a strange prince, called Prince Mammon, who is lately come into that state, and hath taken vp one of the principall houses (belonging to a chiefe noble-man of that countrey) for himselfe and followers ... / translated out of the true Italian copie ; also, the abridgement of the articles of pacification of Italie, made betwixt his Imperiall Maiesty and the most Christian King at Ratisbone, the 13th of October, 1630, both in Latine and English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Includes: An abridgement of the pacification of Italy, made betwixt his Imperiall Maiestie, and the most Christian King at Ratisbone, 13 October, 1630.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Italy --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Germany --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Italy --  Foreign relations --  Germany.</term>
               <term>Germany --  Foreign relations --  Italy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27450:1"/>
            <p>NEVVES FROM MILLAINE.</p>
            <p>The Copie of a Letter written from <hi>Millaine</hi> to
<hi>Venice,</hi> by <hi>Signior</hi> PADRE, concerning a ſtrange Prince,
called <hi>Prince Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> who is lately come into that State, and hath
taken vp one of the principall Houſes (belonging to a chiefe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-man of
that Countrey) for himſelfe and followers; <hi>doth paſſe through the
ſtreets alſo of the Citty in his Coach</hi> with 6. Horſes. Doth viſite
the Sicke of the Plague, and both heale and Kill at his pleaſure, appearing
like a Man, and when hee pleaſeth, vaniſhing into a Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the true</hi> Italian
<hi>Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO, The Abridgement of the Articles of Pacification of
<hi>Italie,</hi> made betwixt his Imperiall Maieſty and the moſt
Chriſtian King at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> the 13. th of October, 1630.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both in Latine and Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for NATH: BVTTER. 1630.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:27450:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27450:2"/>
            <head>THE COPIE OF A LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, written from <hi>Millaine</hi> to
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice,</hi> on the nineteenth of <hi>September, Nouoſtilo</hi> by
Signeor PADRE, as followeth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great wonders we ſee in theſe our Times, preſſe me
to impart the ſame to you, that you may be truely informed what hath happened
here in the City of <hi>Millaine,</hi> within this fortnight; whereof I will
ſet downe nothing, but what I haue ſeene with mine owne eyes. On the
ſixth of this inſtant Moneth of <hi>September,</hi> here appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a
Spirit, (for ſo I muſt call him) that tooke vpon him a humane ſhape,
which calles himſelfe Prince <hi>MAMMON,</hi> he ſeemes to be about the age
of fifty yeares, he weares his beard very long and ſquare cut, he is neyther
leane nor fat, great nor little, high nor low, the colour of his skinne, is
neyther white nor blacke, but is a man of a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſtature, and of a very
cleare complexion. <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27450:3"/>At his
entrance into the City, he appeared in a very faire Caroach of greene Veluet,
embrode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red within and out with Gold, Pearle, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones, which
Caroach was drawne with ſixe ſuch Horſes, as nature neuer framed goodlier
Creatures, all trapped with rich imbrodered Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſuteable to the
Caroach; he was attended with ſixeteene Footmen, young, proper, and
beard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, who with the Coachman and poſtilian, were all futed in
Lyueries of greene Veluet, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brodered with Gold, Pearle and precious Stone,
ſutable to the Caroach and Horſes. The Horſes ſeemed like
<hi>Turkiſh</hi> Gennets, and were of ſuch a compoſure for colour, and
ſhape ſo vndeſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for curioſity, that there was no imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to be found in them; becauſe, when ſo many excellencies meet together, they
make a thing Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall. This Spirit thus humanized, rode through the City,
in the State and Equipage of an Embaſſadour, in a flow motion, till he came
to a goodly Pallace of the Earle <hi>Triuoleheos,</hi> which is ſcituate in
the <hi>Romane</hi> Street, where he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Caroach to ſtay, and
finding the doores thereof faſt barred vp with lockes, and Iron bolts (the
ſaid Earle hauing left his ſayd Houſe, for feare of the infection of the
Plague) he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Seruants to enter, but being told the doores were
faſt, he alighted and came to the doores, and immediately without any
violence, the doores flew open, and he entred and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the ſame
Houſe with forty Beds, for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his retinew, where hee
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27450:3"/>to all that came, and cured
all diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but eſpecially, the Plague, which at this time rageth very
ſore in this place. He can transforme his ſhape at his pleaſure, and day
and night he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth through this City: And when he viſits the ſicke,
he asketh them whether they will be healed, and doe ſuch things as he ſhall
require of of them to doe: if they ſay they will, he heales them immediately,
but if they refuſe or ſticke at the motion, he ſtrikes them with a Rod
that he hath in his hand, and the party ſo ſtrooke dyeth preſently, as it
hath happened to many in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This being knowne to the State, they
conſult with the Prelates; namely, the Cardinall and Byſhop of this
Dioceſſe, and when the Senate of the Clergy had attempted all wayes, both
Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and Temporall, that could be imagined, for the chaſing hence of
this Fury, and could not doe it: at the laſt they concluded, that it was the
will and pleaſure of the Almighty God, to permit and ſuffer him to be
there, for this I know, that after they had ſent the Marſhall with 200.
men, well furniſhed with Piſtols and other munition to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him,
imagining, him to be ſome Witch, or ſuch like Impoſtor, he ſuffered
himſelfe to be attached and carryed to the Priſon gate, where he made
himſelfe inuiſible, and ſo got out of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers hands, and ſhortly
after he was found at his Palace, feaſting &amp; entertaining ſuch as came
to him. Moreouer I hard, that hereupon the Cardinall with the conſent of the
reſt of the Clergy, determined to ſummon him to the Cathedrall Church of
the <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27450:4"/>City, to giue an accompt
to them what he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there to doe, which Summons was giuen on the Friday
fortnight after his appearing in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as he was riding in his Caroach:
vnto which Summons he did yeeld obedience, but with this Prou ſo, that the
ſaid Cathedrall might be ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in fitting manner, to receiue a Prince of
his Honour and Dignity, for (as he affirmed) he was a Prince of 15. Legions,
whereupon there was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receiue him, a ſumptuous Cloth of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,
with Chayres and Cuſhions ſuteable: and vnder his feet was layd a curious
Carpet of Tape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, wrought with ſilke and gold. The night fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his
Summons and proceeding in his Appearance, he ſeemed to ſcatter much Duſt
in the ſaid Cathedrall, and in the Greeke Street, where he knew the moſt of
the people of the City would be, by which meanes it is conceiued, that a great
num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the people were infected; for the next day following, there dyed of
the Plague between 6. and 7000. of this City; but at this time prefixed, he
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come vnto the Cathedrall where all the learned of the City were
aſſembled, he was Interogated, and vnto foure of their Queſtions he made
direct Anſweres. But then ſaid, it was nobleneſſe and Princelike to
vouchſafe to anſwer, and therefore of his benignity and humaine Clemency,
he had anſwered accordingly; but ſaid, he would not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwer them,
vnleſſe with more and greater authority he were compelled thereunto.
Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a Poſt is diſpatched for <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Popes authority
may be had. But after he had ſtayed all <pb n="5" facs="tcp:27450:4"/>further
queſtioning of him, voluntarily, and of his owne accord, he fell vpon a
ſerious diſcourſe of the high myſteries of the moſt ſacred Trinity,
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering ſuch truthes thereof, as their owne Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and
vnderſtandings could not chuſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, wherein he ſhewed ſuch
great learning, that all that were preſent and could vnderſtand him,
ſtood amazed, and aſtoniſhed to heare him: Which diſcourſe when he
had ended, he tooke a ſolemne leaue, and meekly departed to his Pallace,
afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. By which time the Earle <hi>Trinoleheos,</hi> hearing how his
houſe was entred, returned thither full of indignation, but when he came in
preſence of the Prince, he was ſtrucken with ſuch awe and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
that his anger turned into a Courtly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, ſaying: he was infinitely
bound vnto his Highneſſe, that he had ſo honoured him, as to make vſe
of ſo meane a Cottage to be his receptacle: Whereto the Prince replyed, that
he would not proue vngratefull, and therewith tooke a Viall of cleere water out
of his pocket, &amp; ſaid to the Earle, I giue this liquor to your Honor,
which you muſt eſteeme as deare as your owne life, the vertue whereof, is
this, that if you take a dram thereof in pure wine euery morning faſting,
neither you nor your Court, ſhall be in any danger of the Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the
Plague, but may without feare lay your hand vpon a running ſore. We ſhortly
expect the returne of the Popes Authority, which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue will be here with
the next Poſt, and after that I ſhall enforme you of many and almoſt
incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible things: the Prince continues both night and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27450:5"/>day paſſing through all
the parts of the City, at his pleaſure: he ſpends liberally, and eates and
drinks plentifully, and when he will, he can and doth Inuiſibly, and when he
thinkes good, refines his humane ſhape. I haue many things to write vnto you,
which I am forced to omit, vntill the next Poſt, and in the meane time, I
kiſſe your hands:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Millaine</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 19. <hi>of September, nouo Stilo,</hi>
1630.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your aſſured, S. PADRE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="enclosure">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27450:5"/>
            <div type="articles_of_peace">
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                  <head>An Abridgement of the pacification of Italy, made betwixt
his Imperiall Maieſtie, and the moſt Chriſtian King at Ratisbone
<hi>13.</hi> October, <hi>1630.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Peace ſhall bee vniuerſall, not onely in
Italy, but alſo in Germany, neither ſhall the one offend the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any
way, nor either aſſiſt the others Enemies by any meanes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To the Duke of Sauoy for his pretentions to
Montferrato, Trino, and other places in Montferrato ſhall be aſſigned,
the Annuall Reuenues whereof ſhall amount vnto 18000. Crownes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Duke of Loraynes pretenſions are reſerued
vnto ſome amicable Compoſition, or ſome proceſſe by comprimiſe, or
the Emperours iudiciall deciſion, to be performed within the next 6. moneths
enſuing the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſtiture of the Duke of Niuers.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Duke of Guaſtale for his pretenſions to the
State of Mantua, certaine Townes ſhall bee aſſigned, whoſe reuenues
amount vnto the value of 6000. Crownes.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Duke of Niuers ſhall acknowledge his fault in
writing, and demaund pardon thereof.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Likewiſe the Imperiall Maieſtie by the pure
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of the Pope, and the moſt Chriſtian King (to be
interpoſed in writing) ſhall grant the Inueſtiture of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27450:6"/>both the Dukedome of Mantua,
and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. By vigor whereof he ſhall affoord his Imperiall
protection thereof, againſt all thoſe who wil moleſt him.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Preſently after this Treaty, and the
Subſcription of the Deputies of both parties, in the Hall, and n tice giuen
thereof in Italy, all hoſtilities on both ſides ſhall ceaſe.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Then after 15. dayes all <hi>Caeſars</hi>
Souldiers muſt be drawne out of Italy, Mantua, and Canetta reſerued, as
alſo the King of Spaines Souldiers, and within the ſame time likewiſe the
Souldiers of the moſt Chriſtian King, reſeruing Pinnarola, Bricaras,
Suſa, and Auiglia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, and finally the Duke of Sauoy, his Souldiers
reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Trino.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The Citty, Caſtle, and Fort of Caſall, with
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of Montferrat, excepting the aſſigned vnto the Duke of Sauoy,
muſt be reſtored to the Duke of Niuers, which he may fortifie with
conuenient Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons depending onely vpon him.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Then Mantua, and alſo Canetta, ſhall be by
the Emperour conſigned vnto the Duke of Niuers, as alſo Pinnarola,
Bricaras, Suſa, and Auigliana, by the King of France, to the Duke of Sauoy,
and their Garriſons withdrawne from all places.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. The paſſages held in the Valtolina, and the
Forts there erected, the Emperour ſhall cauſe to be reſtored to their
former eſtate.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Hoſtages on both ſides ſhall bee put into
the hands of the Pope, or the great Duke of Tuſcane, or of ſome Catholicke
Prince in Germany, till the premiſes be performed.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. The Commonwealth of Venice ſhall bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
in this Peace, and they likewiſe ſhall withdraw their Souldiers.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:27450:6"/>
                  <p n="15">15. As for the controuerſies concerning the Cities
and Biſhoprickes of Metz, Verdun, and Tull, the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacie of Bruxens, and
other places attempted and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated by the French, in the preiudice of the
Empire, they are remitted to another Treaty to be made, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſtill the
Fort of Moyenarch in it being.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. The Duke of Lorayne likewiſe is included in
this Peace.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. A generall friendſhip is agreed vpon, and a
mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall reſtitution of all immoueable goods on euery ſide, with a free
relaxation of priſoners.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. If the Treaty of Peace commenced in Italy, be
concluded before the ſubſcription vnto this preſent Treaty, in all that
ſhall be ſubſiſted vpon.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. With a firme faith all theſe things are
promiſed by his Imperiall Maieſtie for himſelfe, and the Duke of Sauoy,
and their aſſiſtants, and of the moſt Chriſtian King, by his name
giuen.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Ratisbone</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 13. <hi>of October,</hi>
1630.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <head>Vnderwritten.</head>
                           <item>Antonino <hi>Abbate in Crems Munſter,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ottoliber Barone A Moetiz,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hermanus Liber Barone A
Queſterbarch.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                           <head>On the left hand,</head>
                           <item>Brulart, <hi>Counſellour of the moſt
Chriſtian King,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Frater Ioſephus Cacuſinus.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list> 
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="cover_note">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:27450:7"/>
                  <p>Theſe precedent Artic. we do giue you (gentle Reader) as
we haue receiued them, printed in ſeuerall Languages beyond the Seas, with
aduice that they were ſo conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the Dyet at Ratisbone, but whether
they ſhall be receiued, and ratified on all ſides or not, we doe not as yet
vnderſtand, and therefore we intend, if there comes any certainty thereof to
our hands, to giue it you with our next Curranto.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:27450:7"/>
                  <head>COMPENDIVM Pacificationis Italicae, initae inter
Maieſtatem Caeſ. &amp; Regem Chriſtianiſſimum.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ax erit vniuerſalis, non modo in
Italia, verum etiam in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, neque vnus alterum, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque modo effendet,
aut alter alterius hoſtes quocunque modo vel ratione iuvabit.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Sabaudiae Duci pro ſuis paerten
ſionibus ad Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferratum adſignabitur Trinum &amp; alia loca in
Montferrato, quorum reditus annuatim aſcendant ad <hi>18.</hi> millia
ſcutorum.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Lotharingiae Duciſſae praetenſiones
reſeruantur ad amicabilem compoſitionem vel proceſſum Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promiſsi,
vel deciſionem Caeſaream Iudicialem, ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam intra ſemeſtre
proximum à conceſſa Niuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſi Duci inveſtitura.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:27450:8"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Guaſtallae Duci pro ſuis
praetenſionibus ad ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Mantuanum adſignabuntur certae terrae, quarum
reditus aſcendent ad valorem annuum <hi>6000.</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Nivernenſis culpam ſuam agnoſcet,
&amp; in ſcriptis depreacbitur.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6.</hi> Tum illi Maieſtas Caeſ. praeviâ
interceſsione Summi Pontificis &amp; Regis Chriſtianiſsimi in ſcriptis
interponenda, inueſtituram vtriuſque Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus concedet.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7.</hi> Eiuſque vigore protectionem Imperialem
tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buet aduerſus quoſcunque qui illum vellent mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> Statim poſt Tractatum in aula à
Deputatis v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinque ſubſcriptum &amp; in Italia notificatum,
hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates omnt ex parte ceſſabunt.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9.</hi> Tum intra quindenam abduci debebunt ex
I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia Milites Caeſarei, reſeruata Mantua &amp; Caneto, Milites Hiſp.
Regis, Milites Christianiſsimi, reſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Pignarelo, Bricaras, Suſa,
&amp; Auigliana; Et Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites Ducis Sabaudiae reſeruato Trino.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10.</hi> Cluttas, Caſtrum &amp; Fortalititiom
Caſalenſe alitaque loca Montferrati, exceptis Duci Sabaudiae aſsignatis,
reſtitui debent Duci Niuernenſi, qui illa poterit munire praeſidijs
conuenientibus, &amp; à ſe tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum dependentibus.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11.</hi> Inde Mantua quoque &amp; Caueto ex parte
Caeſ. Ma. Duci Niuernenſi, Pignarolo, Bricaras,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27450:8"/>Suſa &amp; Auigliana ex
parte Regis Chriſtianiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, abductis praeſidijs Duci Sabaudiae
conſignabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12.</hi> Paſſus in Valtellina &amp; Rhaetiae
occupatus &amp; Fortalitra ibidem erecta, Ma. Caeſ. in priſtinum ſtatum
reſtitut ſacret.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13.</hi> Obſides hinc inde dabuntur ad manue
Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Pontificis, vel Magni Ducis Hetruriae, vel Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis alicutus Catholice
in Germania, de nec antedicia compleantur.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14.</hi> Reſpublica queque Veneta in hac pace
inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, ipſa quoque militem ſuum abducere debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15.</hi> Controuerſiae, ratione Ciuttatum &amp;
Eptſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patuum Metz, Toul, &amp; Verdun, &amp; Abbatiae Sorren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, &amp;
quae ibidem locorum attentata vel innouata fuerunt exparte Gallorum in
praeiudicium Imperij, ad alium Tractatum inſtituendum remittuntur, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nente
fortalitio in Magenwick in ſuo eſſe.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16.</hi> Dux Lotharingiae quoque in hoc Tractatu
incluſus eſt.</p>
                  <p n="18">
                     <hi>18.</hi> Si in Italia Tractatus pacis initus
&amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſus fuerit ante praeſentis ſubſcriptionem, illa
prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valebit.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:27450:9"/>
                  <p n="19">
                     <hi>19.</hi> Optima fide haec omnia promittuntur
à Ma. Caeſ. pro ſe, Rege Catholico &amp; Duce Sabaudiae, ſuis
aſsiſtentibus, &amp; lege à Chriſtianiſsimo ſuo, nomine.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dat Ratisbonae
<date>
                           <hi>13.</hi> Octob. <hi>1630.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>Abbas in Kremſmunſter,</item>
                           <item>Otto à Noſtitz liber Baro.</item>
                           <item>Herman à Queſtenberg.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Brulard</hi> Regis Chriſtianiſsimi</item>
                           <item>Conſillarius Status, &amp; Orator fr.</item>
                           <item>Capucinus <hi>Ioſephus</hi> Aſsiſtens.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27450:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
